Guide to the Shenandoah Valley Oral History Project, 2005-2009: SdArch 29
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
- Series 2: Oral History Interviews, 2006–2009
  - 29-27: Anonymous Male, interviewed by Chelsea Hersch, April 19, 2007
    - Preservation master, April 19, 2007 (Box 1, Cd-r SA029-cd-099)
  - 29-28: Arefaine, MicKnai, interviewed by Senay Gebremedhin, April 24, 2009
    - Transcript and supporting documents, April 24, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Original audio-disc, April 24, 2009
  - 29-29: Blakey, Barbara, interviewed by Kristy Kendall, February 23, 2008
    Barbara Blakey discusses her life in Harrisonburg, Virginia. Blakey recalls teaching high school business and English classes at the Lucy Simms school, in Harrisonburg; her work in the NAACP; the advent of public housing in the Shenandoah Valley; and the impact of integration on education in this area.
    - Transcript and supporting documents, February 23, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Original audio-disc, February 23, 2008 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-029)
    - Preservation master, February 23, 2008 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-099)
  - 29-30: Branham, Kenny, interviewed by Joseph Gregory, March 6, 2006
    Kenneth Branham, Chief of the Monacan Indian Nation in Amherst County, Virginia discusses growing up in Amherst, Virginia, the racism he experienced in the public schools, the impact of racism on graduation rates, and his decision to stay in Amherst County rather than join the airforce. Topics he discusses include the "Racial Integrity Law of 1924" and its impact on racial classification on government documents; Walter Plecker and the eugenics movement in Virginia; his family's work in the apple orchards in Amherst County; sweat lodges; his involvement at church; and his efforts to gain federal recognition of the Monacan Indian Nation.
    - Transcript and supporting documents, March 6, 2006
    - Original audio-disc, March 6, 2006 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-030)
    - Preservation master, March 6, 2006 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-095)
  - 29-31: Bruce, David William and Theresa Anne, interviewed by Lara Mack, 2006-11-16T00:00:00.000
    David William Bruce and Teresa Anne Bruce, poultry farmers in Harrisonburg, Virginia, discuss topics such as changes in turkey growing from the 1970s; working for public vs. privately owned companies, and day-to-day tasks of turkey farming; technological changes in farming; methods of turkey growing; costs of growing; the feed industry; and poultry diseases. They discuss their work with Wampler Foods (WLR) and Pilgrims Pride, and their decision to grow toms (male turkeys) for meat consumpution for Virginia Poultry Grower's Co-op (VPGC).
    - Transcript and supporting documents, 2006-11-16T00:00:00.000 (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Preservation master, 2006-11-16T00:00:00.000 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-093)
  - 29-32: Bumbaugh, Edwin C., interviewed by Theodore Dubinsky, April 16, 2008
    - Transcript and supporting documents, April 16, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Preservation master, April 16, 2008 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-093)
  - 29-33: Burruss, William T., interviewed by Jessica Woodward, March 5, 2007
    Records an interview with William T. Burruss, who worked as a turkey farmer in the 1980s and 1990s for Rocco and Cargill. Burruss discusses relationships with supervising companies; the financial side of the poultry farming, including getting loans for improvements; Avian flu and poultry diseases; the challenges of waste disposal; and complying with environmental regulations.
    - Transcript and supporting documents, March 5, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Original audio-disc, March 5, 2007 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-031)
    - Preservation master, March 5, 2007 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-097)
  - 29-34: Capps, John, interviewed by Tiffany Cole, April 11, 2009
    John Capps of Harrisonburg Virginia, discusses his experience serving in the first Persian Gulf War, his involvement with the VFW post in Harrisonburg, taking classes and vocational training, his work as a correctional officer, his experiences raising two children, and goals for his family. Capps also discusses the time he lived at the Valley Mission, a transitional homeless shelter, in Harrisonburg, Virginia. He discusses the rules and social environment at the Valley Mission, and homelessness in Harrisonburg.
    - Transcript and supporting documents, April 11, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Original audio-disc, April 11, 2009 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-032)
    - Preservation master, April 11, 2009 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-095)
  - 29-35: Carr, Norman, interviewed by Matthew Caggin, March 18, 2009
    Records an interview with Norman Carr of Rockingham County, an automechanic who opened the auto repair shop, Strictly Volvos, in Harrisonburg, Virginia. Carr discusses childhood memories, attending the Nashville Auto-Diesel College in Nashville, Tennessee, how he started his shop, Strictly Volvos. Carr discusses various personal physical injuries, changes in the car repair industry, certification and testing requirements for auto mechanics, his own political views about immigration and taxes, his daughter's career in business. Carr discusses crime in Harrisonburg, including an unsolved murder that took place at the L&S Diner in Harrisonburg, and the murder of Ernie James in 1997.
    - Transcript and supporting documents, March 18, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Original audio-disc, March 18, 2009 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-033)
    - Preservation master, March 18, 2009 (Box 1, Cd-r SA029-cd-096)
  - 29-36: Coffman, David, interviewed by Dan Kerr, April 7, 2008
    - Transcript and supporting documents, April 7, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Preservation master, April 7, 2008 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-093)
  - 29-37: Custer, Elizabeth (Libby), inverviewed by Laura Hawxhurst, November 10, 2008
    Records an interview with Elizabeth (Libby) Custer, who worked for the Wampler Foods, later Wampler-Longacre-Rockingham (WLR), until her retirement in the 1990s. Custer discusses growing up on the family farm, the company's beginnings in 1947, her various jobs at Wampler, taking the company public, the takeover attempt by Tyson, and the sale to Pilgrim's Pride. She also discusses the poultry business generally, including changes in dressing and processing turkeys, government regulations, labor and unions, turkey breeding, and relationships with other companies such as Borden and Rocco.
    - Transcript and supporting documents, November 10, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Original audio-disc, November 10, 2008
    - Preservation master, November 10, 2008
  - 29-38: Deavers, Mark, interviewed by Richard Jones, December 7, 2006
    Records and interview with Mark Deavers of Rockingham county, who works as a poultry litter distributor and soybean farmer. Deavers discusses various aspects of the poultry litter business, including the differences between commercial and organic frertilizers, fertilizer storage buildings, fire risk, the impact of fuel prices and commercial nitrogen on his business, various techniques for spreading litter, and his relationships with farmers from Timberville, Harrisonburg and Broadway area. Deavers discusses the Chesapeake Bay Foundation regulations, fertilizer run-off and leaching, complying with state regulations and the Virginia Department of Environmental Quality (DEQ).
    - Transcript and supporting documents, December 7, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Preservation master, December 7, 2006 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-099)
  - 29-39: Elliott, Carolyn Sue, interviewed by Joseph Gregory, March 25, 2006
    Records an interview with Carolyn Sue Elliot, member of the Monacan Indian Nation of Amherst County, Virginia. Elliot discusses her family working in the apple orchards, experiences of racism and discrimination in public school and at Sweet Briar College, the news coverage when members of the Monacan Indian Nation started to attend public schools, and the stigma associated with Monacan last names. Elliot discusses Walter Plecker and the "Racial Integrity Act of 1924," Monacan relations with the Catawba, Iroquis Nation and Sioux, research being done on Monacan culture, sweat lodges, efforts to get federal recognition from the government, and her desire to visit the burial place of Pocahontas, in Gravesend, England.
    - Transcript and supporting documents, March 25, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Original audio-disc, March 25, 2006 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-035)
    - Preservation master, March 25, 2006 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-092)
  - 29-40: Flory, Gary, interviewed by Adam Regula, November 13, 2006
    Records an interview with Gary Flory, who works for the Valley Regional Office of the Virginia Department of Environmental Quality (DEQ). Flory discusses issuing permits, and inspection of agricultural operations, including poultry operations. He discusses nutrient management plans, nutrient analysis of poultry waste, record keeping on litter transfer, water quality assessment, changes in waste management regulations during his tenure, eutrophication, phytase in poultry feed, the impact of various poultry management practices on phosphorous levels in the litter, hormone use in poultry, and other environmental concerns related to pollutants and waste management.
    - Transcript and supporting documents, November 13, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Original audio-disc, November 13, 2006 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-036)
    - Preservation master, November 13, 2006 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-094)
  - 29-41: Flory, Gary, interviewed by Ian Hallada, November 5, 2008
    Records an interview with Gary Flory, who works for the Valley Regional Office of the Virginia Department of Environmental Quality (DEQ). Flory discusses his childhood in Ohio, his education, and previous employment as an environmental consultant. Flory discusses his work as a water compliance manager overseeing waste water treatment plants and inspecting farms and poultry operations. Flory discusses the use of poultry litter as a slow-release fertilizer in the Shenandoah Valley, specifically the issue of excess nutrients in ground water and waterways. He also discusses disposal methods of dead birds, the use of phytase in feed, fish kills in the Shenandoah Valley, the inspection process, bacteria in poultry litter. Flory discusses the work of the Department of Conservation Recreation, and the other groups involved in environmental issues related to the poulty industry.
    - Transcript and supporting documents, November 5, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Original audio-disc, November 5, 2008 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-037)
    - Preservation master, November 5, 2008 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-094)
  - 29-42: Good, Brian, interviewed by Richard F. Jones, December 4, 2006
    Records an interview with Brian Good of Broadway, Virginia, who works as a poultry litter distributor in the Shenandoah Valley. Good discusses his business operation, fuel prices and litter demand, the use of bedding on litter, storage facilities, and other aspects of the business.
    - Transcript and supporting documents, December 4, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Original audio-disc, December 4, 2006 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-038)
    - Preservation master, December 4, 2006 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-092)
  - 29-43: Grower 1, interviewed by Trey VanHout, November 22, 2006
    Records an interview with an anonymous poultry farmer in the Harrisonburg area. The turkey grower discusses best practice and guidelines for poultry management, zoning laws, daily tasks on the farm, working with buyers, poultry diseases and prevention, nutri-management control plans, waste management, and his relationship with area poultry processing companies such as Rocco and George's.
    - Transcript and supporting documents, November 22, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Original audio-disc, November 22, 2006 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-039)
    - Preservation master, November 22, 2006 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-098)
  - 29-44: Grower 2, interviewed by John Profita, April 1, 2007
    Records an interview with an anonymous turkey farmer in Harrisonburg, Virginia. The grower discusses his childhood involvement with 4H and FFA, debt load and other challenges related to the business of farming, and contracts with poultry suppliers. He discusses workplace injuries, poultry feed, poultry breeding and farm mechinization. The grower discusses his involvement with the Virginia Poultry Growers Cooperative (VPGC) and his work with various agriculture-promoting organizations like the Young Farmers Organization.
    - Transcript and supporting documents, April 1, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Preservation master, April 1, 2007 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-098)
  - 29-45: Hadley, George, interviewed by Richard F. Jones, April 15, 2007
    Records an interview with George Haldey, poultry grower in Rockingham County. Haldey discusses how he got into the poultry business after working as a merchant seaman, a history teacher and a duck farmer. He discusses poultry diseases such as avian flu, his thoughts on diversified farming, his contracts with Rocco and George's, and vertically integrated food production.
    - Transcript and supporting documents, April 15, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Original audio-disc, April 15, 2007 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-040)
    - Preservation master, April 15, 2007 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-094)
  - 29-46: Hall, John, interviewed by Meryl Rubin, November 10, 2006
    Records an interview with John Hall, feed mill operator at Southern States Feed Mill, a farmer-owned operation with a store in Harriosnburg, Virginia. He discusses topics such as feed suppliers, genetic engineering, nutrient blends and formulas, poultry feed, the use of additives and medications, government regulations and compliance, logistics, safety hazards and precautions, machine maintenance, and his ideas about the future of the feed industry.
    - Transcript and supporting documents, November 10, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Original audio-disc, November 10, 2006 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-041)
    - Preservation master, November 10, 2006 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-095)
  - 29-47: Hall, John and Charles Smith, interviewed by Dan Kerr and class, February 5, 2008
    NO TRANSCRIPT. There is an index.
    - Transcript and supporting documents, February 5, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Preservation master, February 5, 2008 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-095)
  - 29-48: Hamilton Duff, Victoria, interviewed by Joseph Gregory, March 9, 2006
    - Transcript and supporting documents, March 9, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Original audio-disc, March 9, 2006 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-042)
    - Preservation master, March 9, 2006 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-097)
  - 29-49: Hammond, Marshall, interviewed by Jeffrey Joyce, November 17, 2008
    Records an interview with Marshall Hammond, member of the Shenandoah Valley Bike Coalition (SVBC), in Harrisonburg, Virginia. Hammond disucsses his work as an industrial trainer for Merck & Co. in Elkton, Virginia. Hammond recalls his childhood experiences biking in Martinsburg, West Virginia, racing with "Mennonite kids," and ways he incorporates cycling into his daily life. He discusses the increase of bicycle clubs, bike paths and bicycle shops in this area; the role that the Harrisonburg and Rockingham Regional Pedestrian and Bike Committee has played in increasing bike lines; and the creation of the Rocktown Trails, in Harrisonburg, Virginia.
    - Transcript and supporting documents, November 17, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Original audio-disc, November 17, 2008 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-043)
    - Preservation master, November 17, 2008 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-096)
  - 29-50: Harris, Kendall, interviewed by Matthew Neese, April 20, 2007
    Records an interview with Kendall Harris, a farmer in Christiansburg, Virginia, who sells pasture-raised chickens and grassfed beef. He discusses his daily work, including maintenance, fencing, butchering by hand, dealing with predators, and organic certification. He notes in the influence of farmer and author, Joel Salatin, on his business model.
    - Transcript and supporting documents, April 20, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Original audio-disc, April 20, 2007 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-044)
    - Preservation master, April 20, 2007 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-095)
  - 29-51: Hearl, Lacy, interviewed by Joseph Gregory, March 7, 2006
    Records an interview with Lacy Branham Hearl, a member of the Monacan Indian Nation, living in Amherst County, Virginia, and mother of Kenneth Branham and Marilyn Branham. She describes her childhood, attending the Amherst Mission school for several years, and then going to work in the apple orchards at age eleven; discrimination she experienced as a teenager; the social stigma related to the last name Branham; "Plecker's Rule," referring to Walter Plecker, who drafted the Racial Integrity Act of 1924, and working with lawyers to correct the racial classification on their birth certificates; her family history and childhood memories; attending a public school for the first time; her efforts to learn more about her own ancestory; and her work selling tickets at the annual powwow.
    - Transcript and supporting documents, March 7, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Original audio-disc, March 7, 2006 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-045)
    - Preservation master, March 7, 2006 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-095)
  - 29-52: Hernandez, Sandy and Jacinto, interviewed by Claire Moore, December 2, 2005
    Records an interview with Sandy and Jacinto Hernandez, of Harrisonburg, Virginia, who discuss immigration in Harrisonburg and their work with Alianza, associated with Covenant Presbyterian Church in Harrisonburg. They discuss their personal histories; various immigrant groups in Harrisonburg; Skyline Literacy and Dayton Learning Center; access to health insurance and health care; the Hispanic Chamber of Commerce; and ideas about integration.
    - Transcript and supporting documents, December 2, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Original audio-disc, December 2, 2005 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-046)
    - Preservation master, December 2, 2005 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-097)
  - 29-53: Johnson, Wilhelmina, interviewed by Kristie Kendall, March 14, 2008
    Records an interview with Wilhemena Johnson, who discusses her life in Harrisonburg, Virginia. Johnson, who graduated from the Lucy Simms School in Harrisonburg, Virginia in 1947, discusses her subsequent work at the Harrisonburg/Rockingham Department of Social Services, and involvement with various social services organizations in Harrisonburg. Johnson recalls public school integration in Harrisonburg; the "urban renewal" movement in the 1950s-1960s and its the impact on the black community in Harrisonburg; public housing; the construction of the John Wesley Methodist Church on Sterling Street, in Harrisonburg; segregation in Harrisonburg area businesses in the 1930s and 1940s; the role the Lucy Simms school played in organizations in the community; black-owned businesses in Harrisonburg, and various places of business in Harrisonburg that are no longer in operation. She discusses various families in Harrisonburg, including the Bundy, Newman, Tolliver, Wilson, Harper, Curry, Webb, and Ney families.
    - Transcript and supporting documents, March 14, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Preservation master, March 14, 2008 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-097)
  - 29-54: Keck, Darrel and Supervisor of Sales, interviewed by Helen Murray, December 8, 2006
    Records an interview with Darrel Keck, Executive Director of Sales and Marketing for the Virginia operation of George's, Inc., and an anonymous Supervisor of the Inside Sales Group for Cargill, in Harrisonburg, Virginia. They discuss various aspects of the poultry processing industry, including their suppliers, the relationship to the pet food industry and work with rendering operations, marketing, transportation and distribution costs, international shipping, contracts with poultry growers, avian flu and poultry disease, PETA, product brands including Shady Brook Farms, future products, and their views of future of the poultry industry in Rockingham County. They discuss the acquisition of Rocco, Inc. by Cargill in 2001.
    - Transcript and supporting documents, December 8, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Preservation master, December 8, 2006 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-098)
  - 29-55: Kiracofe, Jeffrey, interviewed by James Dennis, March 13, 2009
    Records an interview with Jeffrey Kiracofe, a turkey grower and farmer in Bridgewater, Virginia. He discusses various aspects of the business, including dealing with poultry diseases like avian flu and cholera, labor issues, farm tools, poultry feed and nutrition, commodities pricing, the impact of fuel prices on his business, litter disposal and poultry waste, competition with other poultry farmers, egg gathering, artificial insemination, sanitation, bio-security, the impact of poultry dust on human health, contract farming, and thoughts about finding different employment. Kiracofe discusses various breeds, including Nicholas, Hybrid and British United Turkey. He also discusses working with Wampler Longacre (WLR), Pilgrim's Pride, the Virginia Poultry Growers Cooperative (VPGC), and Ag Forte.
    - Transcript and supporting documents, March 13, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Original audio-disc, March 13, 2009 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-047)
    - Preservation master, March 13, 2009 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-099)
  - 29-56: Kiracofe, Vallie, interviewed by James Dennis, April 3, 2009
    Records an interview with Vallie Kiracofe who discusses her life and work on a farm in Bridgewater, Virginia. Kiracoffe recalls her childhood on a farm, when her father worked at the lumber mill, raised chickens and sold eggs for a living. She recalls raising four children on a small farm; gardening, cooking, canning and preserving food; cutting firewood for fuel; animal feed; washing clothes by hand; attending church; selling animals at a stock sale in Harrisonburg; relationships with neighboring farmers; her three sons who live nearby, and their work in the cattle business and poultry business. Kiracofe recalls classmates who worked in the factories, staying home to help her mother iwth the house. Kiracofe's grandson Jeffrey Kiracofe and his spouse, Christine were also present during the interview.
    - Transcript and supporting documents, April 3, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Original audio-disc, April 3, 2009 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-048)
    - Preservation master, April 3, 2009 (Box 1, Cd-r SA029-cd-099)
  - 29-57: Layman, Allen, interviewed by Stephen Coords, March 25, 2009
    Records an interview with Allen Layman, an employee of Western State Hospital in Staunton, Virginia, for over 30 years. Layman discusses various positions he has held at Western State Hospital, and his personal views on mental health care and mental health services in this area. Layman discusses his work as president of the local union, his involvement with the Staunton NAACP, and activism related to LGBTQ rights, immigration and healthcare.
    - Transcript and supporting documents, March 25, 2009 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Original audio-disc, March 25, 2009 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-049)
    - Preservation master, March 25, 2009 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-092)
  - 29-58: Lohr, Matthew, interviewed by Matthew Lohr, April 12, 2007
    Records an interview with Matthew Lohr, part-owner of Valley Pike Farm, a multi-generational family farm in Broadway, Virginia. Lohr discusses poultry farming, changing relationships with the major poultry companies, farm safety, dealing with avian flu and poultry diseases, farm credits, their beef and pumpkin-patch businesses, and his work as a representative of the 26th district on the Virginia House of Delegates.
    - Transcript and supporting documents, April 12, 2007 (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Original audio-disc, April 12, 2007 (Box 1, Cd-r SA0029-cd-051)